Claire Auzias Collection
International Institute of Social History
Claire Auzias Collection
1977-1985
ARCH00248
Auzias, Claire
1.20 m. 83.9 GB
International Institute of Social History Cruquiusweg 31 1019 AT Amsterdam The Netherlands
Context
Biographical Note
Born Lyon 1951; French historian, feminist and libertarian; published on the history of the syndicalist movement, anarchism and on the Roma. In 1980 she defended a doctoral thesis in history at Lyon-II University on the oral memory of the libertarian movements in Lyon during the Interbellum.The interviews in this collection form the basis of this thesis. Researcher at the Socius laboratory of the Technical University of Lisbon. Member of the editorial committee of the Revue Chimères. Author of La grève des ovalistes; Lyon juin-juillet 1869, Claire Auzias was interviewed herself by Mimmo Pucciarelli: Claire l'enragée (Atelier de Creation Libertaire, 2007).
Acquisition
Collection donated to the IISH by Claire Auzias in 1985, with an accrual in 2013.
Content and Structure
Content
32 digitized audiotapes and 30 digitized audiocassettes with interviews with libertarians. Transcriptions of interviews, copies of documents, notes and bibliographical references relating to Auzias' publications 'La grève des ovalistes: Lyon juin-juillet 1869' and 'Mémoires libertaires: Lyon 1919-1939'. In the introduction of this thesis Auzias wrote: "Dix-huit militants libertaires furent questionnes des heures durant sur ce que fut leur activite politique et syndicale, leur vie familiale, profesionnelle, associative, culturelle. Tous accepterent notre intrusion dans leur passe avec plus que complaisance, chaleur et soutien. Ils recurent ce projet avec une extreme courtoisie, nous aidant de conseils, directions de recherches, suggestions et remarques qui, souvent, nous tirent d'embarras. Ils mirent a notre disposition leurs temoignages et reflexions, leurs documents prives: presse, brochures, photographies. Ce travail, en remerciements et en symphaties, leurs est dedie: sans eux, il n'eut ete cette approche orale du mouvement libertaire" (Eighteen libertarian activists were questioned for hours about what was their political and trade union activities, their family life, professional, associative, cultural. All accepted our intrusion into their past with more than complacency, warmth and support. They received this project with extreme courtesy, helping us with advice, directions for research, suggestions and remarks that often help us out. They put at their disposal their testimonies and reflections, their private documents: press, pamphlets, photographs. This work, in thanks and sympathy, is dedicated to them: without them, it was not this oral approach of the libertarian movement).
Some interviews (Gaston Illy, 1977) held by Daniel Colson and Annik Houel.
In the edition of 1993 of her thesis she writes more specific on role/profession of her sources (p. 12).
Accrual 2013 (photocopies from CIRA in Lausanne, Switzerland): transcriptions of interviews held by Claire Auzias with Louis Buronfosse 1977, Marius Chabany 1977, Antoine Marsella and Marie-Louise Marsella-Massoubre 1977, 1980, Pierre Masneuf 1978 and Lorenzo Ruiperez 1977, 1979.
Subjects
Geographic Names
France
Persons
Angelini; Buronfosse, Louis; Chabany, Marius; Chirat, Pierre; Eyraud, Janette; Eyraud, Regis; Forgues, Auguste; Illy, Gaston; Lavorel, M.; Marsella, Antoine; Marsella, M.L.; Masneuf, Pierre; Navel, Georges; Navel-Fort, Marguerite; Padros, Jaime; Rosso, O; Ruiperez, Lorenzo
Themes
Syndicalism/Trade unions; Feminist movements/Women's movements; Anarchist movements
Material Type
Archival material; Sound documents; Ephemera; Serials
Access and Use
Access
Not restricted
Used to be 'restricted' with the addition 'to be determined' (acq. 1985).
List
- Audio tapes
  - Interview with Georges Navel. 1978., 1-3; ca. 190 min
    Former Call numbers: BG GB1/962-964.
    - Audio tape 1., 1
    - Audio tape 2., 2
    - Audio tape 3., 3
  - Interview with Marguerite Navel-Fort. 1978-1979., 4-9; ca. 390 min
    Former Call numbers: BG GB1/433 (tape 4) and GB1/965-970 (tapes 5-10).
    - Audio tape 4., 4
    - Audio tape 5., 5
    - Audio tape 6., 6
    - Audio tape 7., 7
    - Audio tape 8., 8
    - Audio tape 9., 9
    - Audio tape 10., 10
  - Interview with Gaston Illy. 1979., 11-13; ca. 170 min
    Former Call numbers: GB1/977-979.
    - Audio tape 11., 11
    - Audio tape 12., 12
    - Audio tape 13., 13
  - Interview with O. Rosso. 1979., 14-17; ca. 340 min
    N.B. Former Call Numbers GB1/980-983.
    - Audio tape 14., 14
    - Audio tape 15., 15
    - Audio tape 16., 16
    - Audio tape 17., 17
  - Interview with Pierre Masneuf. 1978., 18-23; ca. 260 min
    Former Call numbers; BG GB1/984-989.
    - Audio tape 18., 18
    - Audio tape 19., 19
    - Audio tape 20., 20
    - Audio tape 21., 21
    - Audio tape 22., 22
    - Audio tape 23., 23
  - Interview with Jaime Padros. 1979., 24-29; ca. 330 min
    Former Call numbers: BG GB1/990-995.
    - Audio tape 24., 24
    - Audio tape 25., 25
    - Audio tape 26., 26
    - Audio tape 27., 27
    - Audio tape 28., 28
    - Audio tape 29., 29
  - Interview with unknown person 1978., 30-32; ca. 170 min
    N.B. Former Call numbers: BG GB1/996-998.
    - Audio tape 30., 30
    - Audio tape 31., 31
    - Audio tape 32., 32
- Audio cassettes
  - Interview with Pierre Chirat. 5-12-1981., 33-34; 94 min
    NB. Former Call Number: BG GC1/90.
    - Audiocassette 1, Side A., 33
    - Audiocassette 1, Side B., 34
  - Interview with Angelini 1977., 35-36; 76 min
    N.B. Former Call Number: BG GC1/91.
    - Audiocassette 2, Side A., 35
    - Audiocassette 2, Side B., 36
  - Interview with Auguste Forgue 1977., 37-40; 136 min
    N.B. Former Call Numbers BG GC1/92 A-B.
    - Audiocassette 3, Side A., 37
    - Audiocassette 3, Side B., 38
    - Audiocassette 4, Side A., 39
    - Audiocassette 4, Side B., 40
  - Interview with Peau D'Ane alias Louis Buronfosse 1977., 41-42; 28 min
    N.B. Former Call Numbers: BG GC1/93.
    - Audiocassette 5, Side A., 41
    - Audiocassette 5, Side B., 42
  - Interview with M. Lavorel 1979., 43-44; 45 min
    N.B. Former Call Numbers: BG GC1/94.
    - Audiocassette 6, Side A., 43
    - Audiocassette 6, Side B., 44
  - Interview with Regis & Janette Eyraud 1977., 45-46; 39 min
    N.B. Former Call Numbers: BG GC1/95.
    - Audiocassette 7, Side A., 45
    - Audiocassette 7, Side B., 46
  - Interview with Marius Chabany 1977., 47-50; 93 min
    N.B. Former Call Numbers: BG GC1/96 A-B.
    - Audiocassette 8; Side A., 47
    - Audiocassette 8; Side B., 48
    - Audiocassette 9; Side A., 49
    - Audiocassette 9; Side B., 50
  - Interview with Jaime Padros 1977., 51-58; 245 min
    N.B. Former Call Numbers BG GC1/97 A-B-C-D.
    - Audiocassette 10, Side A., 51
    - Audiocassette 10, Side B., 52
    - Audiocassette 11, Side A., 53
    - Audiocassette 11, Side B., 54
    - Audiocassette 12, Side A., 55
    - Audiocassette 12, Side B., 56
    - Audiocassette13, Side A., 57
    - Audiocassette 13, Side B., 58
  - Interview with Odino Rosso 1979., 59-66; 248 min
    N.B. Former Call Numbers BG GC1/98 A-D.
    - Audiocassette 14, Side A., 59
    - Audiocassette 14, Side B., 60
    - Audiocassette 15, Side A., 61
    - Audiocassette 15, Side B., 62
    - Audiocassette 16, Side A., 63
    - Audiocassette 16, Side B., 64
    - Audiocassette 17, Side A., 65
    - Audiocassette 17, Side B., 66
  - Interviews with Antoine and M.L. Marsella 1976, 1977, 1980., 67-78; 314 min
    N.B. Former Call Numbers BG GC1/99 ABC-101 AB.
    - Audiocassette 18, Side A., 67
    - Audiocassette 18, Side B., 68
    - Audiocassette 19, Side A., 69
    - Audiocassette 19, Side B., 70
    - Audiocassette 20, Side A., 71
    - Audiocassette 20, Side B., 72
    - Audiocassette 21, Side A., 73
    - Audiocassette 21, Side B., 74
    - Audiocassette 22, Side A., 75
    - Audiocassette 22, Side B., 76
    - Audiocassette 23, Side A., 77
    - Audiocassette 23, Side B., 78
  - Interview with Lorenzo Ruiperez 1977, 1979., 79-92; 471 min
    NB. Former Call Numbers BG GC1/102-105.
    - Audiocassette 24, Side A., 79
    - Audiocassette 24, Side B., 80
    - Audiocassette 25, Side A., 81
    - Audiocassette 25, Side B., 82
    - Audiocassette 26, Side A., 83
    - Audiocassette 26, Side B., 84
    - Audiocassette 27, Side A., 85
    - Audiocassette 27, Side B., 86
    - Audiocassette 28, Side A., 87
    - Audiocassette 28, Side B., 88
    - Audiocassette 29, Side A., 89
    - Audiocassette 29, Side B., 90
    - Audiocassette 30, Side A., 91
    - Audiocassette 30, Side B., 92
- Typoscripts
  - Previsite Marcel Jaccoud. 2-2-1979., 93; 1 folder
  - Typoscript interviews Lorenzo Ruiperez. 1977-1979., 94-95; 2 folders
  - Typoscript interviews O. Rosso. 1979., 96-99; 3 folders
  - Typoscript interviews Jaime Padros. 1977-1979., 100-102; 3 folders
  - Typoscript interview with Angelini. 1977., 103; 1 folder
  - Typoscript interview Regis & Jeanette Eyraud. 1977., 104; 1 folder
  - Typoscript interview Gaston Illi. 1977-1979., 105-106; 2 folders
- Accrual
  - Typoscript interview with Marius Chabany. 1977., 107; 1 folder
  - Typoscript interview Louis Buronfosse. 1977., 108; 1 folder
  - Typoscript interview Pierre Masneuf. 1978., 109-112; 4 folders
  - Typoscript interview Antoine and Marie-Louise Marsella. 1977-1980., 113-114; 2 folders
  - Typoscript interview Lorenzo Ruiperez. 1977-1979., 115-116; 2 folders
- Notes and documentation
  - On a.o. Spanish civil war, Sacco & Vanzetti, Groupe Libertaire 1928 and 1929. ca. 1979., 117; 1 folder
  - On a.o. "NID rouge". ca. 1979., 118; 1 folder
  - On a.o. Affaire Vial, Front social, Comité d'Action libertaire, Libertaires Italiens a Lyon. ca. 1979., 119; 1 folder
  - On a.o. Groupes individualistes libertaires. ca. 1979., 120; 1 folder
  - On a.o. groupe communiste libertaire. ca. 1979., 121; 1 folder
  - On a.o. Groupe de libre discussion. ca. 1979., 122; 1 folder
  - On a.o. Causeries populaires, groupe esperanto ouvrier, informations biographiques. ca. 1979., 123; 1 folder
  - On a.o. Comité des Syndicats Revolutionaires, CGT-SR (Confédération Générale du Travail-Syndicaliste Révolutionnaire). ca. 1979., 124; 1 folder
  - On a.o. La pensée libre, jeunesse syndicaliste de Lyon. ca. 1979., 125; 1 folder
  - On a.o. Cercle USR. ca. 1979., 126; 1 folder
  - On a.o. coopératives ouvrières, le SFIO. ca. 1979., 127; 1 folder
  - On a.o. Théâtre du peuple, Front populaire. ca. 1979., 128; 1 folder
  - On a.o. groupes libertaires Espagnoles a Lyon. ca. 1979., 129; 1 folder
  - On a.o. Comité de Défense sociale. ca. 1979., 130; 1 folder
  - On a.o. Cercle syndicaliste, jeunesse ouvrière. ca. 1979., 131; 1 folder
  - On a.o. A.D.R 1922-1924. ca. 1979., 132
  - On Premier Mai and A.D.R. 1914-1937. ca. 1979., 133
  - Le Combat and printed matter of CNT. 1930-1970., 134
  - Photocopies of de Progrès- Lyon, 1919-1939., 135
  - Photocopies of Archives Chirat "Le libre Examen", Lyon 1934., 136
  - On a.o. Comité pour la 3ème internationale and Propagande electorale (Nationale et Lyon) 1936. ca. 1979., 137
  - Photocopies librarybooks, before 1940., 138
  - Photocopies on a.o. Affaire Calzan, Cuminal (1918)., 139
  - Photocopies ADR and NID-Rouge (1917-1918)., 140
  - Alphabetical cards: A-J: "Biographie, hommes et femmes des mouvements libertaires Lyonnais; natifs, émigrés ou passants". ca. 1979., 141
  - Alphabetical cards: K-Z: "Biographie, hommes et femmes des mouvements libertaires Lyonnais; natifs, émigrés ou passants". ca. 1979., 142
  - Cards with references literature and " éléments biographiques". ca. 1979., 143-146
  - Newspaper clippings. 1927-1936., 147-148
  - Newspapers Lyon Soir,Le Nouvelliste, Le progrès. 1939-1940., 149